Four years ago, on the TED stage,
قبل اربع سنوات، على مسرح تيد،
I announced a company I was working with at the time
أعلنت عن شركة كنت أعمل معها في ذلك الوقت
called Odeo.
تدعى أوديو.
And because of that announcement,
وبسبب هذا الإعلان،
we got a big article in The New York Times,
حصلنا على مقالة محترمة في صحيفة نيويورك تايمز،
which led to more press, which led to more attention,
والتي أدت لمزيد من المقالات الصحفية، ولمزيد من الإهتمام،
and me deciding to become CEO of that company --
ومن ثم قررت أن أصبح المدير التنفيذي لهذه الشركة –
whereas I was just an adviser --
حيث كنت مجرد مستشارا -
and raising a round of venture capital
وبدأت جولة جديدة من جمع رأس المال
and ramping up hiring.
وتكثيف التوظيف.
One of the guys I hired was an engineer named Jack Dorsey,
أحد الذين وظفتهم كان مهندسا يدعى جاك دورسي،
and a year later, when we were trying to decide which way to go with Odeo,
وبعد سنة حاولنا أن نحدد طريقة نطور بها أوديو،
Jack presented an idea he'd been tinkering around with for a number of years
وعرض جاك فكرة حاول تحسينها خلال عدة سنين
that was based around sending simple status updates to friends.
تقوم علي إرسال تحديثات بسيطة للاصدقاء.
We were also playing with SMS at the time at Odeo,
في ذلك الوقت كنا نلهو مع الرسائل القصيرة في أوديو،
so we kind of put two and two together,
فكأننا أدخلنا المشروعين مع بعضهما الآخر،
and in early 2006 we launched Twitter as a side project at Odeo.
وفي بداية 2006 أطلقنا تويتر كمشروع جانبي لأوديو.
Now, it's hard to justify doing a side project
من الصعب الآن تبرير إقامة مشروع جانبي
at a startup, where focus is so critical,
بخلاف مشروعي الأساسي، في الوقت الذي من المهم التركيز فيه،
but I had actually launched Blogger as a side project
لكنني بدأت من قبل Blogger كمشروع جانبي
to my previous company,
في شركتي السابقة،
thinking it was just a little thing we'd do on the side,
متخيلا انه مجرد شيئ صغير أقوم بعمله بجانب عملي،
and it ended up taking over not only the company,
وانتهى الأمر بسيطرته ليس فقط على شركتي السابقة،
but my life for the next five or six years.
ولكن على حياتي لمدى خمس أو ست سنوات.
So I learned to follow hunches
فتعلمت أن اتبع حدسي
even though you can't necessarily justify them
وإن كنت لا تستطيع بالضرورة تبريره
or know where they're going to go.
أو تعرف أين سيذهب بك.
And that's kind of what's happened with Twitter, time after time.
وهذا بالظبط ما حدث مع تويتر، مرة بعد مرة.
So, for those of you unfamiliar,
لذلك، ولمن لا يعرف،
Twitter is based around a very simple, seemingly trivial concept.
تويتر يقوم على مفهوم بسيط ويبدوا ساذجاً .
You say what you're doing in 140 characters or less,
ما عليك سوى ان تقول ما تقوم به في140 حرفا أو أقل،
and people who are interested in you get those updates.
ثم يستقبل المهتمين بك هذه التحديثات.
If they're really interested,
وان كنوا مهتمين بك حقا،
they get the update as a text message on their cell phone.
فيمكنهم الحصول على التحديثات كرسائل قصيرة على هاتفهم المحمول.
So, for instance, I may Twitter right now
لذا، وعلى سبيل المثال، يمكننى الآن تحديث تويتر
that I'm giving a talk at TED.
بأنني أدلي بحديث لتيد.
And in my case, when I hit send,
وفي حالتي، عند الإرسال
up to 60,000 people will receive that message in a matter of seconds.
يستقبل رسائلي حوالي 60،000 شخص في بضع ثوان.
Now, the fundamental idea is that Twitter
الفكرة الاساسية هي أن تويتر
lets people share moments of their lives
يسمح للأشخاص بمشاركة لحظات من حياتهم
whenever they want,
عندما يريدون،
be they momentous occasions
سواء مناسبات عادية
or mundane ones.
أو مصيرية.
It is by sharing these moments as they're happening
وبمشاركة هذه اللحظات وقت حدوثها
that lets people feel more connected and in touch,
يزيد الناس بإحساس الإتصال بالآخرين،
despite distance, and in real time.
برغم المسافة، وفي الوقت الحقيقي.
This is the primary use we saw of Twitter from the beginning,
كان هذا هو الإستخدام المبدئي الذي رأيناه لتويتر
and what got us excited.
ومن ثم تحمسنا له.
What we didn't anticipate was the many, many other uses
ما لم نتوقعه كان الكثير، الكثير من الإستخدامات الأخرى
that would evolve from this very simple system.
التي من شأنها أن تطور هذا النظام البسيط.
One of the things we realized
أحد الأمور التي أدركنا مدى أهمية تويتر منها
was how important Twitter could be during real-time events.
هي الأحداث التي تحدث في الوقت الحقيقي.
When the wildfires broke out in San Diego,
عندما اندلعت الحرائق في سان دياجو،
in October of 2007,
أكتوبر 2007،
people turned to Twitter to report what was happening
تحول الناس الى تويتر لتقرير ما يحدث
and to find information from neighbors
وللحصول على معلومات من جيرانهم
about what was happening around them.
عما يحدث من حولهم.
But it wasn't just individuals.
ولكنها لم تكن فقط لأفراد.
The L.A. Times actually turned to Twitter to dispense information as well,
فقد تحولت صحيفة لوس آنجلوس تايمز الى تويتر لمتابعة المعلومات أيضا،
and put a Twitter feed on the front page,
ووضعت تليقمة لتويتر بالصفحة الرئيسية،
and the L.A. Fire Department and Red Cross
وإستخدمتها إدارة إطفاء الحرائق بلوس آنجلوس والصليب الأحمر
used it to dispense news and updates as well.
لمتابعة الأخبار والتحديثات ايضا.
At this event, dozens of people here are Twittering
في هذا الحدث، قام العشرات من الأشخاص بتحديث تويتر
and thousands of people around the world are following along
وتابعهم آلاف آخرين
because they want to know what it feels like to be here
لأنهم أرادوا أن يشعروا بالتواجد هناك
and what's happening.
ويعرفوا ماذا يحدث
Among the other interesting things that have cropped up
ومن الأمور الشيقة الأخرى التي ظهرت،
are many things from businesses,
أمور متعلقة بالأعمال،
from marketing and communications and predictable things,
في التسويق والإتصالات وأمور يمكن التنبؤ بها
to an insanely popular Korean-barbecue taco truck
الى مثلا شاحنة شواء تاكو الكورية الواسعة الشهرة
that drives around L.A. and Twitters where it stops,
والتي تتحرك في لوس آنجلوس ثم تحدث تويتر بمكان وقوفها
causing a line to form around the block.
فتتسبب في تشكيل خط حول الكتلة.
Politicians have recently begun Twittering.
بدأ الساسة إستخدام تويتر في الآونة الأخيرة.
In fact, there are 47 members of Congress
في الواقع، هناك أكثر من 47 عضو في الكونجرس
who currently have Twitter accounts.
لهم حسابات على تويتر.
And they're tweeting, in some cases,
وفي بعض الأحيان، يقومون بتحديث حساب تويتر الخاص بهم
from behind closed-door sessions with the President.
من وراء جلسات مغلقة مع رئيس الجمهورية.
In this case, this guy's not liking what he's hearing.
في هذه الحالة، فالشخص لا يروق له ما يسمعه.
The President himself is our most popular Twitter user,
الرئيس نفسه واحد من أكثر المستخدمين شعبية،
although his tweets have dropped off as of late,
رغم أن تحديثاته تراجعت مأخرا،
while Senator McCain's have picked up.
في حين أن تحديثات السيناتور ماكين قد إرتفعت.
As have this guy's.
مثل هذا الرجل.
Twitter was originally designed as a broadcast medium:
صمم تويترالى حد كبير كوسيط إذاعي.
you send one message and it goes out to everybody,
ترسل رسالة واحدة ثم تصل للجميع،
and you receive the messages you're interested in.
ويمكنك إستقبال الرسائل التي تهمك.
One of the many ways that users shaped the evolution of Twitter
واحدة من الطرق العديدة التي شكلت تطور تويتر
was by inventing a way to reply to a specific person
كانت بإختراع طريقة للرد على شخص بعينه
or a specific message.
أو رسالة محددة.
So, this syntax, the "@username" that Shaquille O'Neal's using here
لذا، فهذه الصيغة، @إسم المستخدم، والتي يستخدمها هنا شاكيل أونيل
to reply to one of his fans,
للرد على أحد معجبيه
was completely invented by users,
من إختراع المستخدمين تماما،
and we didn't build it into the system until it already became popular
ولم ندرجها داخل النظام العام الا بعد أن أصبحت معروفة بالفعل
and then we made it easier.
فسهلناها عليهم.
This is one of the many ways that users have shaped the system.
وهذه واحدة من الطرق الكثيرة التي شكلت النظام.
Another is via the API.
شئ آخر هو واجهة التطبيق البرمجية.
We built an application-programming interface,
فقد بنينا واجهة للتطبيق يمكن برمجتها،
which basically means that programmers can write software that interacts with Twitter.
مما يعني أن المبرمجين يمكنهم كتابة برامج للتفاعل مع تويتر.
We currently know about over 2,000 pieces of software
وحاليا نعرف أكثر من 2000 برنامج
that can send Twitter updates --
يمكنها أن ترسل تحديثات تويتر
interfaces for Mac, Windows, your iPhone, your BlackBerry --
ومتلائمة مع ماك، ويندوز، آي فون، وبلاك بيري ..
as well as things like
فضلا عن أشياء أخرى
a device that lets an unborn baby Twitter when it kicks
كجهاز يسمح لطفلك الذي لم يولد بعد تحديث تويتر عندما يركل
or a plant Twitter when it needs water.
أو للزرع أن يحدث تويتر عند إحتياجه للماء.
Probably the most important third-party development
ربما أهم تطوير من طرف ثالث
came from a little company in Virginia called Summize.
جاء من شركة صغيرة بفرجينيا تدعى سوميز
Summize built a Twitter search engine.
أنشئت سوميز محرك بحث لتويتر.
And they tapped into the fact
وقد إستفادوا من حقيقة
that, if you have millions of people around the world
أنه ان كان لديك ملايين من الناس حول العالم
talking about what they're doing and what's around them,
يتحدثون حول ما يفعلونه أو ما يحدث حولهم،
you have an incredible resource to find out about any topic or event
فلديك مورد ضخم للحصول على أي موضوع
while it's going on.
أو حدث وقت وقوعه.
This really changed how we perceived Twitter.
غيَّر هذا طريقة نظرنا لتويتر.
For instance, here's what people are saying about TED.
على سبيل المثال، هنا ما يقوله الناس عن تيد.
This is another way that our mind was shifted,
وهذا جانب آخر من الطريقة التي تغير بها فكرنا ،
and Twitter wasn't what we thought it was.
ولم يكن تويتر ما كنا نظنه.
We liked this so much we actually bought the company
أحببنا هذا كثيرا حتى أننا إشترينا الشركة فعلا
and are folding it into the main product.
ونحاول إدماجها مع المنتج الأصلي.
This not only lets you view Twitters in different ways,
وهذا لا يجعلك ترى تويتر بطرق مختلفة فقط،
but it introduces new use cases as well.
ولكن يعرفك بإستخدامات جديدة ايضا.
One of my favorites is what happened a few months ago
واحدة من الإستخدامات المفضلة لي حدث منذ بضع شهور
when there was a gas shortage in Atlanta.
عندما كان هناك نقص في الغاز بأتلانتا
Some users figured out
وجد بعض الناس
that they would Twitter when they found gas --
أنهم إذا حدثوا تويتر عندما يجدون الغاز،
where it was, and how much it cost --
أين يكون، وثمنه،
and then appended the keyword "#atlgas"
ثم يذيلوه بكلمة “#atlgas”
which let other people search for that and find gas themselves.
حتى إذا ما بحث عنها آخرون، وجدوا الغاز.
And this trend of people using this communication network
وهذا الإتجاه الذي إستخدمه الناس لشبكة الإتصال هذه
to help each other out
لمساعدة كل منهم للآخر
goes far beyond the original idea of just keeping up with family and friends.
تذهب الى ما هو أبعد عن الفكرة الأصلية لمجرد التواصل مع العائلة والأصدقاء.
It's happened more and more lately,
وقد حدث في الآونة الأخيرة الكثير والكثير،
whether it's raising money for homeless people
سواء كان جمع الأموال للمشردين
or to dig wells in Africa
أو لحفر الآبار في أفريقيا
or for a family in crisis.
أو لأسرة في أزمة.
People have raised tens of thousands of dollars over Twitter
جمع الناس عشرات الآلاف من الدولارات بمساعدة تويتر
in a matter of days on several occasions.
في غضون أيام في عدة مناسبات.
It seems like when you give people easier ways to share information,
يبدو وكأنك إن أعطيت الناس وسائل اسهل للحصول على معلومات،
more good things happen.
يحدث الكثير من الأمور الجيدة.
I have no idea what will happen next with Twitter.
ليس لدي أي فكرة عما سيحدث مع تويتر.
I've learned to follow the hunch,
ولكنني تعلمت أن أتبع الحدس،
but never assume where it will go.
دون إفتراض أين سيذهب.
Thanks.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: We're not quite done yet.
كريس أندرسون: لم ننتهي بعد.
So, look, if we could have this screen live.
لذا، أنظر، إذا كان بإمكاننا أن نشغل هذه الشاشة..
This is actually the most terrifying thing that any speaker can do
هذا بالظبط أكثر شئ مفزع يمكن أن يفعله متحدث
after they've been to an event.
بعد إلقائهم خطاب.
It's totally intimidating.
إنه شئ مخيف
So, this would be the Twitter search screen.
هذه هي شاشة بحث تويتر.
So we're going to just type a couple of random words into Twitter.
دعونا نكتب بضع كلمات عشوائية في تويتر.
For example: "Evan Williams."
على سبيل المثال: "إيفان ويليامز."
"Evan Williams, give people more good ways to share information and follow your hunch at TED."
"... إعطي الناس المزيد من المعلومات وتتبع حدسك @ #TED."
"Currently listening to Evan Williams." "Currently listening to Evan Williams." "Evan Williams --"
"...أستمع حاليا لإيفان وليمز."
Oh.
أوه.
"Evan Williams is just dying on stage here at TED.
"...يحتضر إيفان وليمز على المسرح الآن بتيد.
Worst talk ever!" (Laughter)
أسوء حديث على الإطلاق!"
Evan Williams: Nice. Thanks.
إيفان ويليمز: جميل. شكراً.
CA: Just kidding.
ك أ: أمزح فقط.
But, literally in the eight minutes he was talking,
ولكن، حقيقة خلال الثماني دقائق لحديثه
there are about fifty tweets that already came on the talk.
كان هناك حوالي 50 تحديث لتويتر.
So he'll see every aspect of the reaction:
لذلك سوف يرى كل جانب من ردود الفعل:
the fact that Barack Obama is the biggest Twitterer,
الحقيقة أن باراك أوباما هو أكبر مستخدم لتويتر،
the fact that it came out of TED.
الحقيقة هذه خرجت من تيد...
I don't think there's any other way of getting instant feedback that way.
لا أعتقد أن هناك أي وسيلة أخرى للحصول على ردود فعل فورية على هذا النحو.
You have build something very fascinating,
قد قمت ببناء شئ مدهش،
and it looks like its best times are still ahead of it.
ويبدو ان أفضل وقت له مازال في المستقبل.
So, thank you very much, Evan. EW: Thank you.
لذلك، شكراً جزيلاً لك إيفان.
CA: That was very interesting.
كان هذا مثيرا للإهتمام.